<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christus Deus The divinity of our Saviour : asserted and vindicated from the exceptions of the Socinians and others : in a sermon preached at St. Peter's Hungate, in Norwich, upon the festival of St. Philip and St. James, in the year 1673 / by Bernard Skelton, sometime vicar of Hinton.</title>
            <author>Skelton, Bernard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60327</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3933</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37553</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16972051</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16972051</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105565</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60327)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105565)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1159:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christus Deus The divinity of our Saviour : asserted and vindicated from the exceptions of the Socinians and others : in a sermon preached at St. Peter's Hungate, in Norwich, upon the festival of St. Philip and St. James, in the year 1673 / by Bernard Skelton, sometime vicar of Hinton.</title>
                  <author>Skelton, Bernard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ... and Samuel Oliver, bookseller in Norwich,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCII [1692]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Divinity --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XIV, 9 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Socinianism.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105565:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105565:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſtus Deus. THE DIVINITY OF <hi>Our Saviour</hi> Aſſerted and Vindicated, from the Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Socinians</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>In a SERMON preached at St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Hungate,</hi> in <hi>Norwich,</hi> upon the Feſtival of St. <hi>Philip</hi> and St. <hi>James,</hi> in the Year 1673.</p>
            <p>By <hi>BERNARD SKELTON,</hi> Sometime Vicar of <hi>Hinton,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, and <hi>Samuel Oliver</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller in <hi>Norwich.</hi> MDCXCII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105565:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105565:2"/>
            <head>THE BOOKSELLER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THIS Diſcourſe was long ago ſuppreſs'd by the Author, after it had been ſent to the Preſs, and the Copy was loſt. But a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman who lived with the Tranſcriber, retriev'd a Copy, and has, at his own Charge and Trouble, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it to the World; the Author neither correcting nor reviewing it: ſo that whatever Errata's you meet with, all muſt not be laid upon him. This I remember he told me, that if he had put it out himſelf, he would have cut off a great many extravagant Enlargements, (ſo he termed them) which though they paſſed in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, could not but be irkſom to an intelligent Reader, who expects not Words, but Reaſon.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:105565:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105565:3"/>
            <head>THE Divinity of our Saviour Aſſerted and Vindicated, from the Exceptions of the <hi>Socinians</hi> and others.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN 14. part of the</hi> 9th <hi>Verſe,</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He that hath ſeen me, bath ſeen the Father.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ST. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf was not more eminent in the Church of God, than he whoſe Feſtivals we this day celebrate. If <hi>Cephas</hi> was a Pillar, ſo was <hi>James</hi> alſo: And in that pure and primitive Council, mentioned, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. he is ſo far from coming ſhort of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in Place and Dignity, that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Vogue will here give him the Priority: For after he had heard the Opinion of the whole Council, he, as chief of this Divine Convocation, briefly rehearſeth their ſeveral Opinions, and laſtly gives his definitive and determinative Sentence, <hi>That we trouble not them, who from among the Gentiles are turned to God.</hi> And though <hi>Rome</hi> hath raiſed her proud Hills above the Clouds, and ſtretched forth her Neck beyond her Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Churches; yet we know that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was the Mother of us all: There the Goſpel was firſt planted; from thence it was diſperſed through the World: and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105565:4"/>St. <hi>James</hi> was the firſt Biſhop thereof, if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Baronius.</hi> And why then may not St. <hi>James</hi>'s Succeſſors challenge Supremacy, as well as St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s, ſince <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was the Mother-Church? But if St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Confeſſion gave him this Prerogative, St. <hi>Philip</hi> will ſtep in here, and ſay, he made it before him: for in <hi>John</hi> 1.45. he tells <hi>Nathanael, We have found him of whom</hi> Moſes <hi>in the Law and the Prophets did write:</hi> Which is nothing elſe but a Periphraſis of the Meſſiah, and is ſo interpreted by <hi>Nathanael</hi> alſo, <hi>ver.</hi> 49. <hi>Thou art the Son of God, thou art the King of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>But not to make the Apoſtles contend or juſtle for Superiority, ſince they had learn'd of their Maſter, <hi>that he that would be greateſt, muſt be their Miniſter,</hi> and <hi>he that would be chiefeſt, muſt be Servant to all;</hi> it is moſt certain that theſe our Apoſtles were in the number of thoſe Stones which were the Foundation of the New and Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the City of God. Neither in their way were they inferiour to any in the Work of the Miniſtry, and the promoting the Intereſt of the Goſpel: For St. <hi>James</hi> refiding at <hi>Jeraſalem,</hi> hath, as well as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the care of all the Churches, and by his Catholick Epiſtle, confounds Hereſy, confirms the Brethren, advance<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the miraculous Tower of Prayer, particularly that by the Elders of the Church; confutes the <hi>Solifidians;</hi> proves that Faith without Works, is no better than the Faith of Devils, which believe and tremble; that without Works it is dead. And the Doctrine thereof hath been long ſince buried, till of late Years it revived, and gained a Reſurrection at <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ntva.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Philip</hi> preached the Goſpel in <hi>Stythiu,</hi> and found more Humanity among thoſe Barbarians, than with thoſe that ſtiled themſelves Chriſtians: For after awen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105565:4"/>Years Travel in that large and barbarous Country, where, contrary to expectation, both himſelf and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine found a moſt welcome Reception, (ſo eaſily can the meek Temper of the Goſpel triumph over ſalvage Natures, and Giant-like Spirits) he returned to <hi>Hiera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis,</hi> a City of <hi>Syria,</hi> where he encounters and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes the <hi>Ebonites,</hi> thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who denied the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of our Saviour; and there, ſay ſome, he found a Tomb, others a Mar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yrdom. So early had Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks learn'd, as well as Jews, to overwhelm with Stones, whom they could not gainſay by Scripture. If we look into the Goſpel, we ſhall find him, as ſoon as he was made an Apoſtle, making others Diſciples, bringing <hi>Nathanael,</hi> the true Iſraelite, to the King of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> obliging the very Gentiles, making Greeks do Homage to the King of the Jews; and here in this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, whereof my Text is a part, earneſtly intreating to be inſtructed in that Doctrine, for which he was content to die.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shew us,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Father, and it ſufficeth.</hi> And Jeſus ſaith unto him, <hi>Have I been ſo long time with you, and yet haſt thou not known me,</hi> Philip? <hi>He that hath ſeen me, hath ſeen the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble you with any ſubtile and accurate Diviſion of the Words; but from this great Truth here aſſerted by our Saviour, I ſhall raiſe this one Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Doctrine, which is the natural Conſequence of the Words, <hi>That Chriſt is one in Eſſence with the Father;</hi> he is the moſt High God, the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> For if this be true which our Saviour aſſerts, that <hi>whoſoever ſeeth him, ſeeth the Father;</hi> and who dare doubt it, ſince it's Truth it ſelf that ſpeaks it; we muſt rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude, either that he is the Father, which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by all, or elſe that the Father and he have one and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105565:5"/>the ſame Divine Eſſence. For whether we make uſe of rational, ſpiritual or corporal Opticks; whether this Viſion be made by the Eye of the Underſtanding, and we interpret the Words, <hi>He that knows me, knows the Father;</hi> or elſe by the Eye of Faith, and ſo, <hi>He that believes in me, believes in the Father;</hi> or we take the Words properly, and by ſeeing is meant the Action of our corporal and ſenſitive Organ; the reſult will be the ſame, the Conſequence not different. For if it be true, that whoſoever knows or believes Chriſt, knows the Father, the Conſequence will be, what our Saviour aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, <hi>John</hi> 10.30. <hi>That he and the Father are one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to theſe object <hi>Socinus</hi> and the Racovian Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, firſt, That theſe Words can by no means be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the Divine Eſſence, which, ſay we as well as they, is inviſible and inacceſſible to the moſt piercing Eye of poor Mortality, ſince the Angels themſelves are forc'd to vail their Faces. But this is ſo ſenſleſs a ſhift, that they muſt be blind indeed, who cannot ſee how to anſwer it: For who ever was ſo quick-ſighted yet, as to ſpy the Eſſences of Things? <hi>Eſſentia rerum non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currunt in ſenſus.</hi> Who ever look'd upon a Man, and ſpied his Soul, that Bird of Paradiſe, perking upon a little Glandule in the midſt of the Brain, and from thence giving its imperious Dictates to every Member of the Body? Or elſe, what Tube or Spectacles did he uſe, to ſee the Soul diffuſed through the whole, and be wholly in the whole, and yet wholly in every part thereof? Now though when we look on a Man, we cannot ſee his Eſſence, and yet by his Diſcourſe and Reaſon, we ſee and know he hath the Eſſence of a Man: ſo whoſoever looks on Chriſt, though the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence be inviſible; yet ſince he that ſees him, ſees the Father, muſt neceſſarily acknowledg, that he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105565:5"/>hath the Eſſence of the Father, he is one with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he is the moſt High God, the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſay the Objectors, If this be granted, yet the Conſequence you make is altogether illogical; for if it be true, that he who ſees Chriſt, ſees the Father, it naturally follows, that Chriſt is the Father, and not, as you ſay, that he is one in Eſſence with the Father. And ſo, contrary to your own Principles, you confound the Perſons, and make the Son the Father, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Son, which is a Contradiction, and altogether impoſſible.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that the word <hi>Father</hi> in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is taken either eſſentially and abſolutely for God, or the Divine Nature; or elſe perſonally and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively in reference to the other Perſons of the ſacred Trinity. An Example of the latter we have in the Commiſſion of Baptiſm; <hi>Go, and diſciple all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And again, <hi>There are three that bear Record in Heaven, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost.</hi> And an Example of the former we have in thoſe Words of the Jews, <hi>We have one Father, even God:</hi> And of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> chap. 9.6. <hi>His Name ſhall be called Wonderful, Counſellor, The mighty God, The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Father.</hi> Now either the Prophet meant he ſhould be called as he was to be, and then the Everlaſting Father muſt ſignify eſſentially the Eternal God; or elſe he ſhould not be what he foretold he ſhould be called: And ſo there is here no Prerogative of the Meſſiah foretold, but the Prophecy is a mere Scoff, and an iro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Mock of him who was to be the Deſire of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And the meaning is, he ſhould be called the wonderful Counſellor, but he ſhall be only one of no Parts, no Wit, Counſel or Advice: He ſhall be called
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105565:6"/>
               <hi>The mighty God,</hi> but ſhall be only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a poor, weak, ſilly Man: He ſhall be called, <hi>The Everlaſting Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> but ſhall be the moſt deſpicable amongſt the Sons of Men. Now ſince this Interpretation is contrary to the Scope of the Prophet, and the Tenour of the whole Scripture, and it's a Contradiction that in one and the ſame Reſpect the Father ſhould be the Son, and the Son ſhould be the Father; we muſt conclude that the word <hi>Father</hi> in this Prophecy muſt be taken eſſentially for God, or the Divine Nature. And if here and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Places of Scripture, (which my time will not now give me leave to enumerate) the word <hi>Father</hi> is ſo taken, why not in this Speech of our Saviour's? which will make the Senſe clear and obvious to the meaneſt Underſtanding, <hi>He that ſeeth me, ſeeth the Father,</hi> that is, ſeeth God, him who hath the Divine Nature; or elſe, which amounts to the ſame, is one in Eſſence with the Father.</p>
            <p>There is yet an Interpretation more, which is the learned <hi>Hammond</hi>'s, in his Paraphraſe on the New Teſtament, where he ſaith, The Son is ſaid to be the Image of his Father, and <hi>whoſoever ſeeth the Son, ſeeth the Father,</hi> alluding to the Expreſſion of the Apoſtle, where Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>the Brightneſs of his Father's Glory, the expreſs Image of his Perſon.</hi> But this is ſo far from helping our Adverſaries, that indeed it doth both confute and confound them: For though, as they ſay truly, the Image, and that it repreſents, cannot be the ſame; yet the Son cannot be ſaid to be the Image of his Perſon, without he have one and the ſame Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature and Eſſence: For every Image either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the outward Lineaments and Proportions of the thing it repreſents, as a Picture, Statute and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; or elſe together with the out ward Lineaments,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105565:6"/>the Geſture and Motion of the thing it repreſents, as a Mirrour or Looking-glaſs. Thus Man as he was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Holineſs, and had Power given him over the Creatures, did repreſent, or was the Image of God in the Imitation of the Divine Operations, or in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his Power, Juſtice and Mercy: or elſe it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the Nature, Genius, Perſon, and internal Form of that whereof it is the Image. Thus the Son of Man cannot be the natural Image of his Father, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he hath one and the ſame ſpecifical Nature with his Father, and is like him in the Qualities and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments of the Soul: <hi>Non progenerat Aquila Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam;</hi> 'tis a Man only that begetteth a Man; 'tis a Man, not a Horſe or a Lion, can be the expreſs Image of the Perſon of a Man. Thus nothing can be the expreſs Image of Infinity, but what is infinite: And the Son of God, the eternal Son of an eternal Father, <hi>God of God, Light of Light,</hi> is the expreſs Image of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Perſon: As he hath one and the ſame not ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, for the Divine Nature is indiviſible, and can be but one (ſince it is impoſſible there ſhould be more than one infinite moſt perfect Eſſence) but individual Divine Nature and Perfections. And ſo the Words, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Interpretation, amount to thus much, that he that ſeeth Chriſt who is the expreſs Image of his Father's Perſon, ſeeth him who cannot but be of the ſame Nature and Divine Eſſence: And ſo the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is yet more clear and evident, that Chriſt is one with the Father, that he is the moſt High God, the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Words being thus cleared, if there were no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Place of Scripture to prove this great Truth, yet from this alone we have ſufficient Ground to believe it. But the Divinity of the Bleſſed Jeſus is almoſt in every
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105565:7"/>Paragraph, writ in ſuch large and evident Characters, that he that runs may read it: Would you ſee it written by a Sun-Beam? What can be more bright and illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, than that Saying of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy?</hi> 1 Tim. 3.16. <hi>Without Controverſy great is the Myſtery of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs: God was manifeſted in the Fleſh, juſtified in the Spirit, ſeen of Angels, preached to the Gentiles, believed on in the World, received up into Glory.</hi> Here the word <hi>God</hi> is the Subject of ſix Propoſitions together, and therefore according to the Rule laid down by the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, ſignifieth the ſupream Power and Majeſty, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding all others from that Deity. Now that that Text is meant of our Saviour, and not of the Will of God revealed by frail mortal Man, and gloriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived on Earth, as they would interpret the Place, is clear, without they make the Scripture ſpeak Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions; and ſo to be taken up into Glory, be to be received gloriouſly on Earth; and then up is down; above, below; Earth, Heaven.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it is the ſame Word which is uſed by the Septuagint for the Aſſumption of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elijah,</hi> and in the New Teſtament for the Aſcenſion of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; <hi>Mark</hi> 16.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.2. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11, 22. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this being the conſtant Notion of the Word, we muſt either learn a Language which the Scriptures know not, and the Holy Ghoſt never uſe; or elſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own Rule, Jeſus muſt be this moſt High God manifeſted in the Fleſh. Would you read this Doctrine engraven by the Point of a Diamond? Conſult St. <hi>John</hi>'s firſt Epiſtle, <hi>chap.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>We know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding to know him that is true: and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt: This is he true God, and eternal Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105565:7"/>
            <p> To this our Adverſaries object only, That there is a Poſſibility the laſt Words in Grammatical Conſtruction may be referred to the Father. But becauſe the Son is the immediate Antecedent, to which the Relative can properly be referred, 2. The Son is here chiefly treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on, which is the Rule they give for interpreting ſuch Places of Scripture. And, 3. ſince the Reaſon ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, why we are in the true God, is, becauſe we are in the Son, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe the Son is the true God. And, 4. in St. <hi>John,</hi> the conſtant Title of our Saviour is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life. Since, I ſay, all theſe Reaſons are in the Text it ſelf, why the Title of the true God ſhould be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Son, and not here referred to the Father, who indeed is ſpoken of in the Text but at a diſtance, I cannot but conclude that our Saviour is the True God, and Eternal Life, the moſt High God, the God of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we look into the Old Teſtament, we ſhall find many Places which directly ſpeak of the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which are interpreted by the Apoſtles in the New, to be meant of none but Chriſt. If <hi>David</hi> ſay, <hi>The Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites luſted in the Wilderneſs, and tempted God in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart:</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> deſcribes the Hiſtory thereof, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.5, 6. and tells us, <hi>God ſent fiery Serpents to deſtroy them:</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> will tell us, <hi>this God was Chriſt;</hi> 1 Cor. 10.9. <hi>Neither let us tempt Chriſt, as ſome of them alſo tempted, and were deſtroyed of fiery Serpents.</hi> What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed would theſe Men have, if we muſt not believe ſuch Places and palpable Truths as theſe are? Will they make both us and themſelves Idolaters? And yet they do no otherwiſe, who give the Honour and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to the Creature, which is due only to the Creator: for (beſides that God ſaith, he will not give his Honour to another) what I pray you is Religious Worſhip, but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105565:8"/>that Homage, Faith and Obedience, which ought to be paid, and is really due from the Creature to the great Creator? Now as it is impoſſible that God can be otherwiſe than the firſt Cauſe and Creator of all things, and ſo cannot deveſt himſelf of that Soveraignty which he hath over the Creature; ſo it is equally impoſſible that another ſhould have the ſame Homage, Honour and Religious Worſhip with the moſt High God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Idolatry, (and yet we are bound to honour the Son as we honour the Father) unleſs he be likewiſe the firſt Cauſe, the great Creator; which for a Creature to be, implies a Contradiction. Since then the Reaſon of the Law, <hi>viz.</hi> our Obligation to worſhip God upon the Account of Creation, always continues; why not the Law it ſelf, which commands, <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip God alone, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve?</hi> If they ſay their Worſhip of Chriſt is ſubordinate, and directed through Chriſt to God the Father; why then do they call the Romaniſts Idolaters? Why do they not ſhake Hands with <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and kiſs the Pope's Toe, who allows no other Worſhip to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and the reſt of the Saints, than they do to Chriſt, whom they make altogether a Creature? Neither will their Simily of a King and his Son, or a Favourite, do here; for a King may deveſt himſelf of his Royal Authority: but it is otherwiſe with God, he cannot but be the firſt Cauſe of all things, and therefore the Creature will be always bound to worſhip him as ſuch. Now as it's contrary to the Juſtice and Truth of God to command us to worſhip him for the firſt Cauſe, for the Creator, who is but a mere Creature: So ſince we are obliged by Scripture to pay the ſame Homage, Faith and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Son as to the Father, to honour the Son as we honour the Father; we muſt conclude that the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105565:8"/>Son, as well as the Father, is the firſt Cauſe, the great Creator, the moſt High God, the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I will not ſtand any longer to prove the Sun gives Light. Our Saviour himſelf who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the higheſt Reaſon, proves the Truth of this Doctrine in this very Goſpel appointed for this Day, in the Verſes immediately following the Text; from the In-dwelling of the Father and the Son: the Greeks call it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; the Latines, <hi>Circuminceſſio;</hi> but I know not well how to render it. Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Becauſe I am in the Father, and the Father in me;</hi> which is fully expreſſed by the Apoſtle; <hi>For in him,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>dwells the Fulneſs of the Godhead bodily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Argument is drawn from his Words or Doctrine: <hi>The Words,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that I ſpeak, I ſpeak not of my ſelf, but the Father that dwelleth in me.</hi> The Prophets of old ſpake as they were moved and directed by God; but here it is God himſelf that ſpeaks. <hi>God who at ſundry times and in divers Manners ſpake in time paſt unto the Fathers by the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt Days,</hi> ſaith the Divine Author to the <hi>Hebrews, ſpoken unto us by his Son,</hi> his natural Son: The Word being here taken emphatically, as appears by the Oppoſition here made to the Prophets, who are in Scripture-Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſtiled the Children or Sons of God. Never Man ſpake as he ſpake, by his Adverſaries own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; <hi>Vox non hominem ſonat, est Deus certè:</hi> What was blaſphemouſly aſcribed to <hi>Herod,</hi> is moſt certainly true; here <hi>it is the Voice of God, and not of Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Argument is taken from his Works and Miracles; <hi>He, the Father,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>doth the Works, believe me;</hi> ver. 11. <hi>For the very Works ſake they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my infinite Vertue, and demonſtrate my Omnipotency.</hi> The ruffling and roaring Winds, the boiſterous Waves
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105565:9"/>obey his Voice, and the Seas acknowledg the Lord High Admiral of the Ocean, to be aboard: The Fiſh bring Silver in their Mouths to do Homage, and pay their Quit-Rents to their ſupream Lord and Maker: The Loaves and Fiſhes multiply, as receiving another Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from the God of Nature, and the Author of all Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundity: Diſeaſes fly, and the Devils tremble at his Command, and are forced to confeſs, what the Socinians deny, that Jeſus is the Holy One, the moſt High God, the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither will the Objection which they make from the <hi>14th</hi> Verſe of this Chapter, where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He that believeth on him, ſhall do greater Works than he doth,</hi> ſignify any thing; for the Words anſwer themſelves: It is by his Power and Authority they are done, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving on him who is one in Eſſence with the Father; for <hi>whoſoever believeth on him, believeth on the Father.</hi> Jeſus ſaith unto him, <hi>Have I been ſo long time with you, and hast thou not known me,</hi> Philip? <hi>He that hath ſeen me, hath ſeen the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, ſaith carnal Reaſon, this is an hard Saying, who can bear it? What <hi>Hocus-Pocus</hi> Tricks have we here to make two one, and one two? What Legerdemain Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity? What religious Non-ſenſe is this? Can the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be the Son, and the Son the Father? If the Son have the ſame Eſſence with the Father, how then can they differ? Can any thing differ from its own Eſſence? Can it differ from its ſelf? Sure theſe are the Dreams of ſome ſuperſtitious Zealots, whoſe Devotion makes them with the Athenians, build Altars, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt High God, who is the higheſt Reaſon, will not oblige his Creature to believe things contrary to Reaſon, and make us do Violence to our own natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Faculties.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105565:9"/>
            <p> The old Jews thought not of ſuch a Plurality of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in one Divine Eſſence; the Old Teſtament no where mentioneth it: And if we conſult the New, we ſhall find Chriſt's Divinity to be by Donation, not by Eternal Generation; that God highly exalted him, and gave him a Name above every Name: but this was the Reward of an excellent Vertue, of an incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Submiſſion to the Death of the Croſs, and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring Obedience; nothing here of an Exiſtence and Divinity before he was born of the Virgin. 'Tis true indeed, he might be called the Son of God, becauſe the Virgin was over-ſhadowed by the Power of the moſt High; but who ever dream'd, the Antient of Days was con-infantiated, and entred into the Womb of a Woman? If this be true, how could the Father be greater than he? Can any thing be greater than it ſelf? Why doth Chriſt acknowledg that all the Power he hath, was given him of the Father; that he can do nothing of himſelf; that he came not of himſelf, nor to do his own Will, or to ſeek his own Glory? If he be the moſt High God, how comes it to paſs that he is not omniſcient, that he knows not the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that he cannot diſpoſe of Places in Heaven, that he denies himſelf to be good, that he affirms the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be the only true God? How is it, that he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Commands from God, to be ſent into the World? What makes him to pray? What, did he put up his Petitions to himſelf? If he be God, how could he die, and be raiſed again by the Power of his Father? And laſtly, why doth he give this as the only Reaſon why he is ſaid to be the Son of God, becauſe he was ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Father, and ſent into the World? Thus you ſee theſe <hi>Zamzummims</hi> of Reaſon would deſpoil the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the higheſt Reaſon of his Divinity. But
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105565:10"/>as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid to his Servant, <hi>There be more with us than with them;</hi> and if that one, who is more than all, be for us; if the <hi>Chariot and Horſemen of Iſrael</hi> be on our ſide, let <hi>Socinus</hi> and his Followers do what they can, I doubt not but we ſhall prevail againſt them.</p>
            <p>The time allotted for this Exerciſe, will not give me leave to anſwer diſtinctly to every one of theſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. I will therefore reduce them ſummarily into Heads and Claſſes; and by applying an Anſwer to each Head, let you ſee eaſily how you may give a diſtinct Solution to every Argument in particular.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, ſaith the Objector, it is againſt Reaſon. To this I anſwer, That it may be above Reaſon, as to the manner of explaining it; but that it is contrary to right Reaſon, I deny; for Reaſon, that Divine Candle of the Lord, hath diſcovered the neceſſity of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to her chiefeſt Adorers. To paſs by <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> and others, whoſe Writings are ſuſpected; what made <hi>Plato</hi> in his fourth Book of Laws, ſay, that God ſhould be the Rule and Meaſure of all things, principally if any where he took upon him the Nature of a Man? Why did <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſay, it was neceſſary the Gods im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſhould veſt themſelves with Humanity, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Errors were crept into the World? <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith, The time will come, when there ſhall be but one common Lord and Maſter, God himſelf, who ſhall reign upon the Earth. Beſides, the Platoniſts plainly aſſert in their Writings, that there are three Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or Perſons in the Deity. Either theſe Men found out this by the Light of Nature, and then how can it be contrary to Reaſon? or elſe they had it by Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Jews, and then it ſeems the old Jews un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it. And certainly it is the Doctrine of the Old Teſtament as well as the New.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105565:10"/>
            <p> But Reaſon ſhews the neceſſity of this Doctrine from one of her firſt Maxims or Principles: Every Good, ſaith ſhe, the more communicative it is, the better it is: if God then be infinitely good, he muſt be infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communicable, which can no otherwiſe be, but by Communication of the Divine Eſſence, which is only infinitely good: ſince the Creatures neither ſeparately nor conjunctly, can any way be ſaid to be ſo. Thus Reaſon ſpeaks a neceſſity of this Doctrine. Are not the Communicator and the Communicated diſtinct Perſons? Yet there can be but one individual, though communicable Divine Eſſence, ſince there can be but one infinitely Good and Perfect, as Reaſon dictates, and we all confeſs.</p>
            <p>But to this they object, That the Son, as infinitely Good, muſt alſo be infinitely Communicable, and ſo <hi>in infinitum.</hi> To this I anſwer, That the Act of Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Communication, is infinite and eternal, and the Eſſence communicated is infinite; how then can there be more than one infinite and eternal Act of Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Where ſhall ye next begin, ſince this can never be at an end? But if you urge the Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt; I anſwer, That every thing which is begotten proceedeth; but not every thing that proceedeth is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. <hi>Eve</hi> was produced and came forth of <hi>Adam,</hi> and yet was not generated by him: So the Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt cannot prejudice the eternal Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame. For though the Eſſence be the ſame which is communicated from the Father to the Son, and from the Father and Son to the Holy Ghoſt; yet there is a difference in the Communication, the Word being God by Generation, the Holy Ghoſt by Proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So that though there cannot be more than one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite and eternal Act <hi>in ſuo genere,</hi> in its kind, by way
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105565:11"/>of Underſtanding, which in ſpiritual Beings is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception or Generation; ſo it's no contradiction, that there be an infinite Act of the Will too, by way of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Love or Volition, which is Proceſſion.</p>
            <p>But, ſaith the Objector, if it be neceſſary that an infinite Good be infinitely communicable, how can theſe two be one? as it is indeed the uſual Method of our Adverſaries to poſe us with the manner of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of a Plurality of Perſons in one Divine Eſſence. But who knows not, that as to argue from the Exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the manner of exiſting, is no Conſequence? ſo to argue we know not the manner of it, therefore it is not, is very bad Logick. We know not how the Loadſtone drills and draws the Iron into its cloſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, but we are ſure it is ſo. The Wind we know blows; but whence it comes, and whither it goes, we are ignorant. In theſe, and a thouſand things more, is Reaſon pos'd in Naturals, much more in Supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals: So that it is a ſufficient Anſwer to ſay, Scripture and Reaſon tell us it is ſo; but how it is ſo, we know not: Neither do we deſire to know, left with the <hi>Bethlemites</hi> we ſmart for our peeping into the Ark of the Lord. But we are not altogether in the dark as to this neither: There is ſomething in Nature, (which tho there be no proportion between finite and infinite) may yet at the leaſt ſhadow out ſomething not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unlike this Plurality of Perſons in one Eſſence. If we lift up our Eyes towards Heaven, and look upon the Sun, we cannot but perceive ſome Glimmerings of this great Truth in that beautiful and glorious Body: Is it not the Fountain and Cauſe of natural Light? Was it ever deſtitute of this pleaſing Act of Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Did it not, ever ſince it was a Sun, ſend forth theſe bright and joyful Emanations? Thus the Son of God
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105565:11"/>is the Brightneſs of his Father's Glory, the eternal Son of an eternal Father. Are not the Sun and its darling Light diſtinct Suppoſites? Do they not differ as Cauſe and Effect, Begetter and Begotten? It is a poor ſhift here to ſay, that Light is a Quality; for Reaſon in the beſt of Antients, <hi>Democritus, Epicurus,</hi> and generally in all the modern Philoſophers, ſpeaks the contrary. In ſhort, the Sun naturally and neceſſarily produceth Light. Thus God, who is the moſt free Agent in this great Act of Generation, acts <hi>ex neceſſitate Naturae,</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, which is the higheſt Perfection, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; becauſe being infinitely Good, he is infinitely Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable. Now that the Sun and Light, which, as Cauſe and Effect, Begetter and Begotten, have one and the ſame individual Eſſence, appears from the tacit Conſent of all Men I ever met with: for if nothing interpoſeth between the Rays of the Sun and them, they will ſay, they are in the Sun: And it is true, for the Sun is Light, and Light is the Sun; they are one in Eſſence, tho diſtinct as Cauſe and Effect. I could enlarge much upon this Similitude, and make it clearer than the Sun it ſelf. But Time calls me to anſwer their other way of arguing, which is by Scripture, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I will be as conciſe as may be, for I fear I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy tired your Patience.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſay our Adverſaries, his Divinity was by Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as appears from <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9. And again, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is called the Head, nay the God of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I anſwer; All this is in reſpect of his humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as we may ſee in the Chapter cited, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. for he that was in the Form of God, and thought it no Robbery to be equal with God, took upon him the Form of a Servant, ſubmitting to the Death of the Croſs, the Puniſhment of Slaves and Servants. The
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105565:12"/>Exaltation therefore of the Humane Nature, as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his Death and Suffering, could be no prejudice to his Divinity, which the Apoſtle aſſerts fully in the foregoing Verſes.</p>
            <p>But, ſaith the Objector, how can the Son be the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? To do nothing of himſelf, not to come of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or ſeek his own Glory, are Imperfections not ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Divine Nature. I anſwer; What he calls Imperfections, are the greateſt Perfections: for ſince the Divine Nature can be but one Chriſt, if he be the proper natural Son of God, as he is ſaid to be in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, muſt have the ſame individual Eſſence with the Father, and ſo conſequently, what the Jews affirmed for Blaſphemy, the moſt High God: and he doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of himſelf, becauſe the Father that dwelleth in him, worketh together with him. <hi>Opera Dei ad extra ſunt indiviſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third ſort of Objections are from thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which deny ſome Perfections to belong to Chriſt, in ſome certain Reſpect: But our Adverſaries deny them abſolutely, as not to know the Day of Judgment, and the like.</p>
            <p>The fourth Objection is, when they attribute ſome Imperfection to Chriſt abſolutely, which is ſpoken of him in Scripture only in ſome certain Reſpect, as to be Man, to Die, to Pray, to be Raiſed again; that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is greater than he, and the like; all which are ſaid of him only in reſpect of his Humanity.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſaith the Objector, Chriſt gives this as the only Reaſon why he is ſaid to be God, becauſe he was ſanctified, and ſent into the World. And here I beg your leave to be more copious; and that I may not ſeem to derogate, or take any thing from the ſtrength of the Argument, I will repeat the very Words of their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105565:12"/>as they are ſet down in the Racovian Catechiſm, <hi>pag.</hi> 19. Having premiſed, that the word <hi>God</hi> is taken two ways in Scripture; firſt, for the moſt High; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for him who hath ſome ſublime Dominion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him; they add, that in the latter Signification, the Word of God is in certain Places dignified with the Title of God. And this we prove, ſaith the Racovian Catechiſm, from the very Words of the Son himſelf, John 10.35. <hi>If ye call them Gods to whom the Word of God comes, and the Scripture cannot be broken: Say ye of him whom the Father hath ſanctified, and ſent into the World, Thou blaſphemeſt, becauſe I ſaid I am the Son of God?</hi> By this Speech Chriſt doth clearly intimate both that the word <hi>God</hi> is ſometimes attributed in Scripture to them who are far inferiour to that one God; as alſo that he called himſelf the Son of God for no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than becauſe he had been ſanctified by the Father, and ſent into the World.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, <hi>1ſt,</hi> That I admit the diſtinction; but that the word <hi>God</hi> is applied to Chriſt only, in the latter Signification, is falſe, as I have before proved: And to ſay only, as they do, that in certain Places of Scripture, the Word, when attributed to Chriſt, is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, in the latter Signification, for him that hath ſome derivative Power from the moſt High God, makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt us: for in certain other Places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it is attributed to Chriſt, in the former Significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the God of Gods, or the moſt High God. If indeed they had ſaid, that in every Place of Scripture, where the word <hi>God</hi> is applied to Chriſt, it is taken only for him who is inferiour to the Supream God, they had ſpoke to the purpoſe. And if this be their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105565:13"/>Meaning, which I think it is, yet what they offer for Proof, is altogether illogical and non-cogent: For who that ever pretended to Reaſon, ever went about to prove an univerſal Affirmative by one Particular? and yet they do no otherwiſe here, for thus they argue; Chriſt calls himſelf the Son of God, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a God in one Place of Scripture, <hi>viz. John</hi> 10.36. wherein the word <hi>God</hi> is uſed in the latter Signification for him that hath ſome derivative Power from the moſt High God, and for no greater reaſon, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is fanctified, and ſent into the World; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in every Place of Scripture, where the word <hi>God</hi> is aſcribed to Chriſt, it muſt be ſo taken, and for the ſame reaſon. Now help me Logick, if this be found Reaſoning, and good Argumentation! The King of <hi>England</hi> is called and acknowledged King of <hi>France</hi> by us here in <hi>England,</hi> therefore he is ſo in <hi>France, Spain, Italy,</hi> and all the World over. Who is ſo dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted, as not to perceive this egregious <hi>non-ſequitur?</hi> But ſuppoſe, what cannot be granted, that he called himſelf God for that reaſon, yet it is not expreſſed, that he calls himſelf ſo for no greater; he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare this, and conceal others at this time, when the Jews were about to ſtone him, for ought our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries can ſay to the contrary. Nay, what if he doth not at all alledg this Reaſon for his calling of himſelf God? which indeed he doth not, as will appear from the conſideration of the Context. The Jews, <hi>ver.</hi> 34. accuſe him of Blaſphemy, and becauſe, <hi>thou being a Man, makeſt thy ſelf a God.</hi> Our Saviour anſwers to this Accuſation, <hi>The Scripture calls them Gods to whom the Word of God came;</hi> therefore if I am ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified or ſet apart by the Father, and ſent into the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105565:13"/>World to preach this Word, I am no Blaſphemer, though I call my ſelf God. It is one thing to ſay, I call my ſelf God, becauſe the Father hath ſanctified me and ſent me into the World; and another to ſay, If I call my ſelf God, for that Reaſon I am no Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer: for Chriſt doth not here go about to ſhew how he is ſaid to be God; but to anſwer their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, and prove that he was no Blaſphemer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaid he was the Son of God. So that the Senſe of the Words is clearly this, I am no Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer by calling my ſelf God, ſince being ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Father, I ſpake nothing contrary to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which calls them Gods to whom the Word of God came.</p>
            <p>And now I hope I have brought to the ground this high and mighty Objection, having ſhewn firſt, that the word <hi>God</hi> (which is ſuppoſed, not granted) be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to Chriſt in the latter Signification, for him that hath ſome derivative Power from the moſt High God; yet in certain other Places of Scripture (when attributed to him) it is taken for the God of Gods, or the moſt High God.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly,</hi> If they mean (what is falſe) that in every Place of Scripture where the word <hi>God</hi> is given to our Saviour, it is taken only for him, who hath ſome deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative Power from the moſt High God; yet their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is not good, becauſe it concludes from one ſole Particular, an univerſal Affirmative.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly,</hi> Becauſe if he does give his Sanctification and Miſſion as a Reaſon of his Deity; yet it cannot be ſaid he called himſelf God for no greater Reaſon, ſince it is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105565:14"/>not ſo expreſſed in the Text, and he might declare this, and conceal others at this time, when the Jews were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſtone him, <hi>His Hour,</hi> as he ſaith elſe-where, <hi>being not then come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4thly,</hi> and laſtly; He doth not ſay, he calls himſelf God for that Reaſon, but ſaith only that if he call him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf God, for that Reaſon, he is no Blaſphemer; his Deſign being not to ſhew how he was God, but to prove he was no Blaſphemer. So that I think now we may ſafely enough conclude, that <hi>he that ſees the Son, ſeeth the Father;</hi> that Jeſus is one in Eſſence with the Father, that <hi>he is the moſt High God, the God of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</p>
            <p>There are yet two Difficulties, the Independency of Chriſt, and the Union of the Divine and Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; both which I will briefly ſpeak to, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, ſay the Socinians, Chriſt is ſaid in Scripture to be the Son of God, and therefore (ſince the Divine Eſſence, which is infinite and moſt perfect, cannot be multiplied without a Contradiction) Chriſt depends on the Father as to his Eſſence, which is an Imperfection not ſuitable to the moſt High God. In ſhort, ſay they, Chriſt is dependent, therefore not the moſt High God.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, 1. That nothing can be ſaid to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon another as to his Eſſence, but what is in time after that which cauſeth it; 2. That hath an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence individually diſtinct from it; 3. Which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105565:14"/>as to its Eſſence, or is in the Power of another to be, or not be. But nothing of this can be ſaid of Chriſt; for the Father and the Son are co-eternal, nei-before or after other; the Son hath not an Eſſence di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the Father; neither is the Son of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent as to his Eſſence: It is not in the Power of the Father, that he be, or not be, ſince the Father naturally and neceſſarily begetteth the Son. In a word, they have both the ſame Eſſence, and how the ſame can be ſaid to depend upon it ſelf, is a manner of ſpeaking I am not acquainted with, and know not how to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. <hi>I am the firſt and the laſt;</hi> which Elogy the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the moſt High God, appropriates to himſelf, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.12. Now I would fain know how the firſt Being can be ſaid to depend upon another for its Being. If our Adverſaries ſay, as they do, that theſe Words are not to be underſtood abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but in reference to the Goſpel or Way of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; then they contradict their own Principles, and take away the Difference between the firſt and ſecond Cauſe. They make the Son the firſt Cauſe, and yet they ſay the Father is the firſt or prime Author of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and ſo in reference to Salvation there is a firſt before a firſt, which implies a Contradiction. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therefore, that theſe words are to be underſtood of Chriſt abſolutely, <hi>viz.</hi> that he is the firſt, being the Cauſe of all things, that <hi>he is Alpha and Omega, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and End, the firſt and the laſt;</hi> which denotes not only his Eternity, but likewiſe his Independency; For how can that which is before all things, be ſaid to depend on any thing?</p>
            <p>As to the Union of the Divine and Humane Nature
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105565:15"/>into one Perſon, our Adverſaries thus argue; It's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that two endued with oppoſite Properties, ſhould combine into one Perſon: Or, that two Natures, each whereof is apt to conſtitute a ſeveral Perſon, ſhould be united into one Perſon.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Firſt, that is neither ſtrange, impoſſible, nor, as our Adverſaries ſay, repugnant to ſound Reaſon, that two Subſtances, endued with oppoſite Properties, ſhould combine into one Perſon: for the Soul is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and the Body mortal; yet theſe do ſo combine that they conſtitute one Perſon. Again, the Soul is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apt to conſtitute, but is really a Perſon, according to the Platoniſt, (if a Perſon be a ſingular Subſtance en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with Reaſon) before its Entrance into the Body; for if each Soul did ſubſiſt by it ſelf many thouſand Years before its Body, it could not be ſaid to be part of a Man before it was united to the Body. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Nature which is not only apt, but really conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes a Perſon, may be united to another Nature, as that both ſhall conſtitute one Perſon. There is no Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity therefore in the Hypoſtatical Union, that there ſhould be two Perſons, and ſo conſequently two Chriſts; for as the reaſonable Soul and Fleſh is one Man, ſo God and Man is one Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And it is falſe, what our Adverſaries ſay, that the Similitude holds not, becauſe according to us Chriſt is both God and Man; but Soul and Body are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined, that a Man is neither Soul nor Body, for he is both. Thus the Scripture, ſpeaking of Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſays, <hi>So many Souls were added to the Faith:</hi> And the common Speech is thus, is there any Body, or there
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105565:15"/>is no Body, meaning none of Mankind in ſuch or ſuch a Place. But if they will not, the Platoniſts Pre-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of Souls, which I, as Anſwerer, am not obliged to prove, but they to diſprove; yet according to the common Opinion, that two Perſons cannot combine, there is no Fear there ſhould be two Perſons in Chriſt; for nothing can be ſaid to be a Perſon, (as your own Definition of a Perſon intimates by the word Individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al) unleſs it actually exiſt: But the humane Nature of Chriſt never exiſted, but in the ſecond Perſon of the Trinity. It is true if the humane Nature had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuated, and ſubſiſted of it ſelf, before it was united to the ſecond Perſon of the Trinity, there might have been ſome Shew of an Objection; but this they know is not admitted. How then can Chriſt be ſaid to be more than one Perſon, ſince the Son of Man ſubſiſts only in the Perſon of the Son of God? What hinders then that a Perſon may be ſo united to another Perſon, which if it ſhould ſubſiſt of it ſelf, would be a Perſon, that they both be one only Perſon, ſince the one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the other, and hath no proper Subſiſtence of its own? But it will be ſufficient in ſhort to ſay, <hi>Rem ſcimus, Modum neſcimus;</hi> the thing we know, the manner we know not: And it is no good Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as I ſaid before, to argue, you know not the manner, you know not how the thing is, therefore it is not.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore admire and adore that infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodneſs of God, which hath revealed ſo much of that great Myſtery to Mankind, which the Prophets foretold, and the Angels themſelves deſired to peep into, <hi>viz. God manifeſted in the Fleſh;</hi> whereby
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105565:16"/>
               <hi>he that ſees Chriſt, ſeeth the Father,</hi> ſees the inviſible God, and approacheth to that Light which is inacceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Would you then ſee the Father? Is your Soul a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſt for the living God? Do you breath and pant af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eternal Life? Why then do you any longer gaze and gape after Vanity? Look upon Jefus, there is no ſeeing the Father, but by the Son: View him in his Word, view him in his Works; <hi>in him dwelleth the Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Godhead bodily:</hi> He only can ſhew you the Father; <hi>He is the Way, the Truth, and the Life;</hi> he only can give you the Ante-paſts of Eternity, and whilſt you are here upon Earth, make you touth Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with a Finger: And though now, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>you can ſee him but as through a Glaſs, darkly;</hi> yet the time will come when you ſhall ſee him as he is, <hi>Face to Face,</hi> encircled with all his Rays of Glory. Again, would you ſee the Father? Doth the Horror of your Sins afright you, and the infinite Juſtice of an angry God terrify you? Have you been bitten by the fiery Serpent, and would you ſee the Bowels of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and the tender Compaſſions of a Father? Look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Jeſus, view him on the Croſs; ſee how he ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth his Arms to receive thee. How can'ſt thou now chuſe but cry out with the Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>O the Depth and Length and Breadth of the Love of God in Chriſt Jeſus!</hi> Behold him bleeding, there's Balſam in his Blood. The Serpent upon the Pole of the Croſs can cure all the venemous Stings of Satan, that red Dragon, that fiery Serpent. Let not the infinite Juſtice of God any longer terrify you: He that ſeeth Jeſus, ſeeth alſo the Father of Mercies, the God of Comfort and all Conſolations. As there was infinite Puniſhment due, ſo there is an infinite Satisfaction made; for he that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105565:16"/>himſelf for us, was both God and Man. <hi>By the Blood of God,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>we are redeemed;</hi> and Jeſus is this God, for he is, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, Rom. 9.5. <hi>over all, God bleſſed for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>To him therefore, with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed, as moſt due is, all Honour, Glory, Praiſe, Might, Majeſty and Dominion, both now and evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Glory be to thee, O Lord.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
